A Guide to the Richard Henry Dana Sr. and Jr. Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6966-b
Richard Henry Dana Sr. and Jr. Collection 1840-1881
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6966-b
ca. 100 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit, 1964 Jun 10
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - "The Little Beach Bird", 1864; AMsS, 2 p.
    [Poem by Richard Henry Dana Sr.]
  - "The Buccaneer", 1871; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Poem, 2 verses, by Richard Henry Dana Sr.]
  - "The Buccaneer", 1854 Jun 27; AMs
    [Poem, 1 verse, by Richard Henry Dana Sr.; in ALS 1854 Jun 27 Richard Henry Dana Sr. to A.D.W. French.]
- Letters
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to James Abraham Hillhouse, 1840 Sep 26; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sending copy of Richard Henry Dana Jr.'s sea journal [Two Years Before the Mast]; discusses public interest; mentions visit from a sailor who had sailed with Dana Jr. and who reported sailors' interest in the book.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to Sarah N. Arnold, [1840?] Nov 21; ALS, 3 p.
    [Responds to the Arnolds' invitation to stay with them in New Bedford when he lectures; mentions attending a John Braham concert; refers to a note from a Mr. Morison.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to Unknown, 1841 Oct 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [Re prospective lecturing in New York, Brooklyn and Baltimore for correspondent and/or Edward Terry or [Edward L.] Keyes; says he has "none but his old lectures"; has heard Dana Jr. in twice in court and comments he did well.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to James Deshon, 1841 May 28; ALS, 2 p.
    [Re obtaining a pew seat for Deshon; says Dana Sr. had already given away family pew seats.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to Leonard Jarvis, 1844 Jan 12; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses Washington Allston anecdotes; mentions his planned book on Allston; tells of the recovery of an earlier part of Allston's "great picture" (Belshazzar's Feast) which had been painted over.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to Jonathan Mason Jr., [1846?] Jun 15; ALS, 2 p.
    [Invites him to see "the great unfinished picture" again in Allston's Cambridgeport house.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charles Eliot Norton, 1847 Sep 28; ALS, 3 p.
    [Arrangements for a walking trip together in Manchester, Mass.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to R. I. Burbank, 1848 Apr 28; ALS, 1 p.
    [Asks about Cincinnati reputation of Dr. Morton whose Cincinnati debts had been settled by Burbank; some of Morton's opponents had spread rumors in Boston he says are untrue.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Samuel Gridley Howe, Wendell Phillips, William Jackson, 1850 Mar 22; ALS, 2 p.
    [Declines invitation to meeting since he disagrees with some of those arranging it who are "in favor of dissolution of the Union"; mentions his dissatisfaction with "Mr. Webster's course" (referring to Daniel Webster's 7th of March speech advocating the Compromise of 1850).]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Erasmus D. Beach, 1851 Apr 13; ALS, 1 p.
    [Requests copy of ( Massachusetts state Senator) Beach's report and bill; biographical note on Dana on bottom of letter in different handwriting.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to William A. Jones, [1853]; AL, 3 p.
    [Mentions daughter's poor health, his own aging, his Poems and Prose Writings and lack of financial reward from writing, and Jones' publications; questions point of preparing lectures for publication; discusses his seashore home and dissatisfaction with Hammatt Billings' sketch of it in Homes of American Authors. Signature cut off and on of Dana Jr. glued on.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to Chauncey K. Williams, 1853 Apr 29; ALS, 1 p.
    [Identifies writer of letter sent him by correspondent as William Stedman, who married his mother's sister; both were daughters of William Ellery whom Dana Sr. saw often "at my father's."]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Henry B. Osgood, 1853 Oct 29; ALS, 1 p.
    [Refuses invitation to lecture.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to A. D. W. French, 1854 Jun 27; ALS, 1 p.
    [Brief cover note with a one verse quotation from "The Buccaneer."]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to John Prescott, 1858 Feb 13; ALS, 2 p.
    [Agrees to advise correspondent and sets appointment for him.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to "President of the Convention", 1858 Oct 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [Enthusiastic endorsement of Charles Francis Adams for Congress.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to James Ripley Osgood, 1859 Jun 14; ALS, 1 p.
    [Asks him to send copy to Father Hicks, editor of The Catholic World. Pencilled note from Osgood on letter top signed "J.R.O." asks someone to be sure this has been done.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to Jonathan Mason Jr., [1862] Dec 25; ALS, 1 p.
    [Tells of Mrs. Washington Allston's death.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to Jonathan Mason Jr., 1864 Aug 6; ALS, 1 p.
    [Expresses sympathy for Mason's son's death.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to J. Cist, [1864] Dec 17; ALS, 1 p.
    [About location of Dana Sr.'s signature on a photograph.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to William Pitt Fessenden, 1867 Feb 8; ALS, 4 p.
    [Queries Fessenden if he had changed his opinions of the proposed Fourteenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution; mentions Massachusetts voters' indifference and a strong party forming against the proposal because under it, the United States has to admit the states, the proposal retards the progress of other proposed Fourteenth Amendments, Massachusetts voting requirements could be affected, and if it were rejected a better course of action might be adopted; says he is writing to Fessenden only and will keep secret his reply or use it as Fessenden desires.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to James T. Fields, [1867]; ALS, 2 p.
    [Unable to take part in Fields' "Dickens' Dinner" any time that week.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to William Maxwell Evarts, 1868 May 17; ALS, 4 p.
    [Expresses disgust about machine politics, Senate's consideration of the articles of impeachment of President Andrew Johnson, and his own failed efforts "to stem the tide" in Massachusetts; mentions views of [Robert Cummings] Schenck. Part of this letter has been cut away, but not the signature.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to "Proprietors of [ ] Globe", 1868 Jun 15; ALS, 1 p.
    [Places order for the "President's Trial."]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1869 Jul 16; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Bon voyage letter to future son-in-law recommending sightseeing in England and a tailor and clothiers.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Sampson, Low and Co., 1870 Oct 17; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [His preference for the Fields, Osgood, and Co. sketch of the brig to that in Sampson, Low and Co. edition of Two Years Before the Mast; requests minor changes and an accounting.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to Jonathan Mason Jr., ca. 1870; ALS, 1 p.
    [Recommends Mrs. Hooper have Walter Brackett clean Washington Allston's picture,"Elijah Fed by Ravens"; mentions poor health. Note on letter mentions subsequent ownership of the Allston painting.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to C. L. Street, 1871 Mar 15; ALS, 2 p.
    [Responds to query about a monument for Samuel Finley Breese Morse; says Professor Francis Dana not his brother or uncle but a remote relative and honored friend of his father and will forward compliment to Francis Dana's widow.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana, 1871 Aug 3; ALS, 3 p.
    [In Portland where he is arguing a case; mention her sisters Lily Dana, Henrietta Dana, and Sally Dana who is feeling much better; left 25 pages of manuscript "on board" with Captain Burke.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1871 Oct 12; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Expresses concern for him and his family (after the Chicago Fire).]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1871 Oct 16; ALS, 3 p.
    [Sending Lyman and his brother book on fire insurance.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1871 Oct 18; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    [Giving permission to announce engagement to daughter Charlotte Dana. ]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1871 Nov 29; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Letter accompanying Charlotte Dana's journal from Europe. ]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1871 Dec 22; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Forwarding Lyman's letter to Charlotte Dana in Stuttgart, Germany. ]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1871 Dec 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [More about Charlotte Dana's European journal.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Feb 13; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Asking about job offer received by Lyman.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana, 1872 Feb 25; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Tells her of trust set up by Aunt Sarah's will providing dowries for Dana's daughters; settlement will be either yearly allowance or down payment for a house.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Feb 29; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Re Lyman's plans in the "new" Chicago and Charlotte Dana's financial expectations upon her marriage.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Apr 27; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    [Re Charlotte Dana's savings transfer to Lyman for deposit on Chicago lot.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Jun 4; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    [Re Lyman's Englewood( Chicago) lot purchase; includes draft and offers some money to obviate need for mortgage.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Jun 4; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    [Re news of Charlotte Dana's European journal; mentions Mrs. Dana is in Baden Baden while Henrietta Dana, Charlotte Dana, and Rosamund Dana are at Cadiz. ]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Jun 18; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Sends money to pay off lot mortgage when it comes due.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Jun 20; ALS, 2 p.
    [Suggests he may prefer to use all the money to avoid a mortgage and may put a lot in Dana's name.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Jun 21; ALS, 4 p.
    [Responding to Lyman's request for advice about changing his profession, discusses law and business professions; suggests he examine his own "duties and purposes in life."]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Jul 11; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Agrees to send more money for a third lot in Englewood and the title to be in Lyman's name.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Jul 25; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Cover letter for lot purchase money with torn list of college boat race times.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Aug 5; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Apologizes for forgetting to endorse check; amusing critique of Harvard- Amherst boat race.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Oct 1; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Congratulates him on becoming a Notary Public; discusses real estate and pleasure in reading Charlotte Dana's last European journals.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Oct 14; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Re Charlotte Dana's Englewood real estate; transactions were to equalize Charlotte's financial situation with her sisters'.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1872 Oct 29; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Thanks him for mentioning another available lot but cannot spare the money for the investment.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1873 Feb 6; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Re Lyman's interests, current activities, family news, opinion of the new Hawaiian sovereign, and his own law practice; mentions health.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1873 Feb 22; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Discusses merits of law school vs. study with individual lawyer; hopes Lyman's parents will visit Boston; regrets missing Mr. Jackson; expresses enjoyment at Lyman's account of the new king of Hawaii and proposal to abstract to the Advertiser, with due safeguards as to its authorship.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1873 Mar 31; ALS, 4 p.
    [Critical discussion of Middlemarch; mentions his admiration and describes the novel as a depressing picture reminding him of "that deary waste of afterthoughts" watching a ship's wake at night.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to William Adolphus Wheeler, 1873 May 26; ALS, 1 p.
    [Asks him to reserve the volume of Sir W. Hamilton. ]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1873 Jun 12; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Thanks for returning Charlotte Dana's journals; asks that Lyman sell Chicago lots or not as he sees fit.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1873 Jun 16; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Further comments on law training, the excellence of Harvard Law School and his pleasure if Lyman were to be nearby, and the excellence of Charlotte Dana's journals; asks that proceeds from sale of Dana's lots not be invested in railroad property.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana, 1873 Jun 30; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Re deeds, property, shipping receipts for furniture but none for portrait; Lyman may attend Harvard Law School; Lily Dana well enough to sail with Dana.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1873 Aug 7; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [To sail with Lily Dana for Europe where he will learn more of Lyman's plans from Charlotte Dana; recommends Harvard Law School as best course for Lyman.]
  - C. J. Kino to Richard Henry Dana Jr., 1873 Aug 28; ALS, 2 p.
    [ London tailor thanks him for his business; sends prices for clothing.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana, 1873 Aug 31; ALS, 4 p.
    [Written on House of Lords stationery while waiting in lobby; mentions Lily Dana's poise in London with his friends Lord Frederick Cavendish and Lord Kinnaird; mentions visit to St. Paul's with Leferve, an hour with Canon Liddon and plans for Dover via Canterbury, then Brussels, then etc.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1873 Oct 1; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Concerns clothing made for Lyman by London tailor Kino.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana, 1873 Oct 24; ALS, 4 p.
    [Re apartment for Charlotte, her trunks, furniture and other personal affects.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana, 1873 Oct ?; ALS, 1 p.
    [Relays Isabelle Dana's invitation for her to stay in Chestnut Street since Dana Jr. and family will be away.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Samuel C. Cobb, 1874 Jan 2; ALS, 2 p.
    [Has a heavy cold but will try to attend invitation to dinner a honoring King of Hawaiian Islands.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charles Deane, 1874 Oct 12; ALS, 1 p.
    [Unable to send copy of Dana's speech although complimented by request.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Alexander N. Harris, 1874 Oct 28; ALS, 2 p.
    [Confirms Harris' position in philosophy and history committees from list in his possession, rather than the list Mr. Cabot had used.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1874 Nov 20; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Tells of Aunt Betsey's death and asks him to relay news to the David Lymans.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana, 1875 Aug 22; ALS, 4 p.
    [Account of "White Mountain Style" drive to join family for vacation in Bethlehem, N.H. and mentions plans to visit North Conway. ]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana, 1875 Sep 8; ALS, 3 p.
    [Mentions family vacation in Manchester, Mass. and drive to the Loring Museum.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana, 1875 Sep 11; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    [Mentions strong northeaster blowing at the shore and the Olmsteads.]
  - Sara Watson Dana to Charlotte Dana, with Richard Henry Dana Jr. note added, 1876 Sep 15; AL, 2 p.
    [Passes on housekeeping hiring details from mother; best wishes to her future husband from Dana Jr. who mentions the > Tribune's comments on [Benjamin Franklin] Butler and "poor" letters of Pierpont to it.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to James R. Osgood and Co., 1876 Dec 21; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks for volume of Tennyson's "Harold."]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana Lyman, 1877 Jan 3; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Mentions family's great concern that she and her husband might have been in the train wreck near Ashtabula in route to Chicago; sends draft and bridal money; misses her.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana Lyman, 1877 Jan 16; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Expresses pleasure at Richard Dana's engagement to Edith Longfellow; attempts to cheer up Charlotte and Francis Ogden Lyman who are both sick.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana Lyman, 1877 Jan 27; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Forwarding Mary Dana's gift to her soon; Dana's reception for Richard Dana and Edith Longfellow; guests included Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, Rev. Sam Longfellow, Mrs. Nathan Appleton, Mrs. Child, Mrs. Greeley Curtis; Dana Sr. unable to come.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana Lyman, 1877 Jun 9; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Concerns Charlotte's journals; Dana's family visits to Hyde Park; status of his law cases; mentions Frank Dana. ]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana Lyman, 1877 Jun 12; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Recommendations to Charlotte on safety of banks; mentions Sally Dana's birthday.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana Lyman, 1877 Jun 25; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Disappointed she cannot come East this summer; mentions family news and health of Dana Sr. and Aunt Charlotte.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana Lyman, 1877 Sep 5; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Distressed Charlotte and Francis Ogden Lyman lost all their money in a bank failure; asks what they need and whether she lost her money from the trust.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Bayard Taylor, 1877 Nov 23; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks for his many kind acts and particularly for something Taylor has written in the Tribune. ]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana Lyman, 1877 Dec 23; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Advises she take books Dana Sr. wishes to give her even if she must store them.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana Lyman, 1878 Feb 6; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Re engagements of two friends.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana Lyman, 1878 Feb 11; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Glad she is taking the books; mentions social news.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charles Deane, 1878 Nov 1; ALS, 2 p.
    [Letter of introduction for Lt. Governor Archibald of Nova Scotia. ]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Harriet Jacobson, 1878 May 1; ALS, 1 p.
    [Complies with her request; expresses interest in aspirations of the young; includes Dana Sr.'s autograph.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Angela Henrietta Channing Dana, 1878 May 17; ALS, 1 p.
    [Asks for prompt receipt of enclosed check and earlier one; love to both daughters and pleasure that they will see Charlotte Dana Lyman soon.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Charlotte Dana Lyman, 1881 Jan 19; ALS, 1 p.
    [Re family financial business.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to unknown, n.y. Feb 15; ALS, 1 p.
    [Apologizes for mislaying check.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to Jonathan Mason Jr., n.y. Oct 24; ALS, 1 p.
    [Regrets delay in sending some papers but just received keys to trunk they are in.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to unknown, n.d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Accedes to complimentary request.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Sr. to E. Smith, n.d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Concerns "packet delivery" and the Manchester Express Co.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Howes Norris Jr., n.d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Brief lines with autograph and favorite sentiment.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to unknown, n.d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Specifying "S. W. Dana" lettered on case for his wife.]
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to unknown, n.d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Fragment. Autograph apparently cut from a letter; a few words of which appear on verso.]
- Miscellaneous
  - Richard Henry Dana Jr. to Massachusetts Constitutional Convention, 1853 Jul 29; DS
    [Receipt for travel and attendance pay due him.]
  - C. J. Kino to Francis Ogden Lyman, 1873 Sep 2; D
    [Receipt for clothing.]